Do that one thing for the glory of God.
You've been listening to Tending the Garden of Our Hearts,
Meditations for Orthodox Families,
with Elisa Bielatech and Christina Wenger.
Elisa also hosts Raising Saints in Everyday Orthodox
on Ancient Faith Radio,
and you'll find her books in our bookstores.
Christina hosts Let Us Attend on Ancient Faith Radio,
and writes for the Orthodox Christian Parenting Blog.
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever,
You're listening to
ancient faithradio.com.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirit.
angels, demons, and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat,
secular materialism, to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young
post this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, all of you giant killers and dragon slayers.
You are listening to Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host, Father Stephen D'Young,
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen D'Amick in Emeas, Pennsylvania.
And if you're listening to us live,
you can call in at 855 AF radio.
So that's 8552372346.
And our very own Matroska Trudy is taking your calls tonight, which we're going to get to in the second part of our show.
It's our annual Halloween special.
It's that beautiful night on the podcast when everyone thinks we're going to weigh in on whether trick or treating is okay.
Or whether you should do trunk retreat or harvest festivals in the church parking lot or whether Halloween is secretly paying in.
But instead we talked about mocking and beating up demons.
because that's what Christianity has always done.
So whether you utterly reject Halloween as all the work of the dark powers or celebrate it as
their defeat, one of the themes that we see connected with Halloween is the theme of madness.
And that's what our show is about tonight. We're going to be talking about how insanity is depicted
in ancient sources, the transformation of human beings by insanity, and whether there is any
discernible difference between mental illness, divine madness, and demonic possessions. So my first
first question for you, Father Stephen, because it's always-
is the big slow pitch of the beginning.
It's whether it's actually possible to experience
what Freddie Mercury sings in Queens 1991 single,
I'm going slightly mad.
That may be possible.
However, when it comes to madness tonight,
we're gonna go one step beyond.
And not just slightly mad, we're going whole hop.
And because it won't fit in later,
and you mentioned weighing in on trick or treating,
I feel like I need
to give to our audience, especially the late teenage, maybe even into college age, members
of our audience, my trick-or-treating cheat code.
All right, here we go.
Okay, so this is the trick-or-treating cheat code.
Here's what you do.
So, this year it will be easy because Halloween is on a Monday, right?
So which means you could do this Tuesday morning.
You need to do this on the
the first weekday morning after Halloween.
You go to a well-to-do suburban area of your town.
You go there about 10, 10, 30 in the morning.
Go door to door, say trick or treat.
When they look at you weird, you say, you give it excuse.
He said, I had to take my kid brother or sister
for retreating yesterday.
I didn't get to go, whatever you want to say, whatever your conscience will allow.
But here's what happens.
The housewives who are at home do not want the leftover candy in their house.
And therefore you will receive without having to wear a costume, without having to engage
in any effort, whole bags of candy.
I feel like you've done this.
I have absolutely done this.
not recently, but it works.
This is the cheat code for trick or treating.
So to all of you high school and college age listeners,
I give this to you free of charge.
I ask only that you in turn pass it on to the next generation.
I've always wondered though, like, what would happen?
I mean, because I'm always interested in getting weird looks
from people, what would happen if we went, like if Orthodox went
trick or treating on the eve of our own All Saints day,
which will be the
like what in June or just what, you know, October 31st on the old calendar. It really,
really, yeah, wait 13 more days. Hey, everybody. See, then the full calendar Western right,
the trick is totally a thing. Yeah. Yeah. But the morning after that's the trick. Yeah.
So, but now, so tonight, because last year was our first...
edition was the monster manual. Tonight is our second edition, so it's the
Monstrous Compendium. And this is apropos not only because it's the second
edition, but the old heads out there will know that when the Monstrous
Compendium was originally released, it was a three-ring binder.
That's right!
Into which Ruth's sleeve supplementary pages were played.
Yeah.
As you bought expansions.
And what we're going to be talking about tonight is actually a collection of loose leaf
pages taken from last year's episode.
That's true.
We're never broadcast.
Because yeah, because last year, I mean, we're not exactly known for going short, although
I'm kind of hoping that I can get home a little bit earlier tonight because I have to get
very early.
Yeah, we went, I think we went...
I think three hours are close to that last year.
And yet we had another whole act worth of material.
Right?
So that's kind of what we're doing this time.
Yes.
So this is the supplement that we are
placing in a new three-ring binder to deliver it to you
tonight.
In an incredible strain on the metaphor.
I think now it's just PDFs.
Everybody just has bootleg PDFs.
Not in my room.
Anyway.
Old man yells at clouds.
But so as mentioned, we're going
to be talking about madness and madmen and mad women,
because we're not sexist.
And how that was seen in the ancient world,
how that's been seen historically, examples of those trends
that we see in scripture or your book.
because on one major biblical example,
and then what that means in terms of our experience
in the church.
And so in the ancient world, and I say ancient world now,
because this goes beyond the ancient Near East.
This is pretty much everywhere, right?
Yeah, right.
The depiction of the mad man or the wild person,
is that that person is treated not just as being mad or outside of the regular social order,
but as also having some kind of connection to the spiritual or the divine.
And we see kind of the polarity of people who are sort of set out.
side the social order through a relationship with the divine.
I say polarity because there's two figures, right?
In the relationship in the epic of Gilgamesh
between Gilgamesh and Enkidu.
So Gilgamesh sort of stands outside
and in his case sort of above the regular social order,
even of a rook where he's king.
by virtue of the fact that we're
told he is two thirds divine, right? He is two thirds of calo, right? He's a giant for those who
get excited about such things, right? So that places him as a sort of God king, right? His peers
are not even like the noble people or the upper class of Uruk. His peers are the gods, right?
Right, right, these above the human social order.
Inca do-
right, the wild man who's out in the wilderness, right, also stands outside that social order,
but on the other end, right, he's hairy all over, he's like a beast, right, or like an animal,
right, despite being human, right, and that wildness is taken in the text to be just as much evidence
evidence of his
quasi-divine status as Gilgamesh's exalted position is of his. And the element
of being disassociated from the social order is very important here. So Aristotle and
his politics says this. He says that he presents human beings as political animals,
right that that we are just constant
It's part of human nature that we live in community.
Yeah, and we as a political and in the sense of, you know, government necessarily just the
police, you know, the city, the society.
Right.
And that could be ordered in various different ways, but that we have these social structures.
Whether that's, you know, a nomadic clan that's biologically related or a Greek city
state or whatever, right, that we live in a community.
Right, we live in a society, right? So we have this kind of social order. And Aristotle even says,
in order to live outside of any kind of social structure, one has to be either a beast or a God.
Right? That means you're either superhuman or subhuman, right? Right? Right.
Right. And that's what what allows you to to live in that way.
Yeah, there's a...
Yeah, otherness of a very deep deep nature. Right, right. And this kind of thing was seen to be a result
generally as we mentioned of some kind of
contact with the divine
Which took different forms, right? This could be in the context of an experience
This could be in the context of something ongoing
So for example Socrates has a demon.
says that dwells within him, right, that that whispers wisdom to his soul. And that divine spirit
in his mind that is within him allows him to stand outside the social order of Athens
and thereby critique it and question it. Right. He's not sort of fully part of it. He's not sort
of immersed in it, but he's able to stand outside of it in order to ask questions about basic
matters of justice and that kind of thing.
And that kind of idea, that of course is where we get the word genius.
Right? So we've talked about before on the show
when sacrifices were offered, whether it was incense or animal sacrifices or cakes or whatever it was sacrificed.
It was sacrificed to the emperor in Rome.
It was actually being sacrificed to the genius of the emperor.
Hmm, the dev-
spirit of the emperor. And there are statues of various emperors starting with a
gustus where they're holding a sort of spirit that to us looks kind of like an
angel because it's a little winged spirit thing, like in their hand. That is
supposed to be their genius. It's supposed to represent that spirit, right? That
divine spirit that causes the emperor to stand above and apart. But it also
also conveyed what we mean by genius.
Yeah, right.
It's very, very gifted in an almost superhuman way.
Right.
And that allows them to rise above what is common and normal for humans.
But just as we have the idea today of the eccentric genius, right, Albert Einstein couldn't
manage the coma's hair.
you know, 20
of the same suit because he didn't want to spend time thinking about what to wear.
You know, we have we have this image that's always been included there too.
Hmm. That's always a little weird. Part of this giftedness. Yeah, part of this being able to
stand apart from society also makes you at least a little off, right? Like it's that being separated
from society creates this certain uncannyness and oddness when compared to the social
structures. And so this gives us the idea of there being individuals in these different
ancient cultures who are sort of touched by the gods, touched being another word for that
encounter. Yeah, right. For for contact or or in or in old southern American English touched.
Yeah, he's a bit or touched touched in the head. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, that's right.
But one of the
is that that was not seen as a negative thing.
Yeah.
Even when we're talking about somebody like Enkidu,
right, who's this wild man, right?
Enkidu, by virtue of being this sort of wild man
who's been touched by the gods,
that's what makes him worthy to be Gilgamesh's friend.
I mean, some of the I have a whole new take on that TV show,
Touched by an Angel.
It's just...
Sorry.
Lots of, yeah.
That was the Roma Downey one.
Yeah, that was always a weird title to me.
Because it's like Roma Downey just went around like
touching people.
Touching people's faces in public or something.
I mean, that would have been a very different show.
It's a kind of rested problem.
But so this wasn't considered a negative thing.
In any of these ancient cultures, in fact these people would be
sought out for their wisdom for their
divine perspective, right?
Always a little like dangerous, right?
Well, yeah, because they're off.
Right?
You don't fit.
You know, quite know what you're gonna get.
Yeah, yeah.
But, you know, if you can find them,
you can hire the eight, no.
You can find these people, and potentially,
because they stand at this remove, right?
They can advise you in a way
that normal people.
hand. Right. And so we even see this and we're going to talk more about this later in the show.
We see this in as we talked about in our episode on prophecy and prophets. We see this in some of
the Old Testament prophets and we see this with holy fools within the Christian tradition.
that there is a treasure of those who have had a kind of contact with.
with God, with Yahweh, the God of Israel, and that contact with Him has removed them from
the regular culture and society in a certain way.
Yeah, they're kind of not right in a certain way.
But the same dynamic pertains that they're seen to have wisdom though, based on that,
to be able to convey things.
We'll get into that more a little bit later, but now...
I'm going to say something nice about Michelle Foucault.
This might be the one nice thing there is to say.
I don't know.
There might be a couple of other things.
Well, I was going to say, as he had a nice idea here, but he was completely bald.
So, you can't even do that.
But so, I don't want to spend too much time talking about Foucault himself, right?
there's an early Foucault and a late Foucault.
And the transition from early Foucault to late Foucault involved
him being in the California desert and taking loose
energetic drugs.
And I know we have some listeners who are fans of psychedelics,
but actually late Foucault is worse.
Yeah, don't do drugs.
Late Foucault is worse than early Foucault.
So the psychedelics did not help him.
Um, that's, but one of
the first one of the first majorly important things that Foucault wrote and you
can see how this would fit into his kind of post structuralist project was
called madness and civilization a history of insanity in the age of reason
which basically is a history of the concept of insanity or madness right sort of
in the Western world especially focusing on Western Europe because he was French.
And what's interesting about this is he kind of constructs a genealogy of the idea of madness.
And how the way in which people view madness and insanity and then mental illness, how that is changed over time.
Yeah. And how certain social construct element to the whole thing.
Right. Right.
Right. That that what it meant to be mad in ancient Greece.
It meant to be mad in medieval France, what it meant to be mad in early modern England and
what it means to be mentally ill today are not the same thing, even though we're using
similar terminology.
So he talks about, he starts by talking about, by talking about what we were just talking
about.
world this was seen as this spiritual
or metaphysical reality, right, that people saw someone who was outside the social orders
being having some kind of special contact with the gods, right, and that it was not a negative
thing.
But then he shows how as we get into the medieval period in Western Europe, how insanity
becomes and madness becomes
a sociopolitical category where someone who is opposed to some element of the current
social order or unable to adapt to it or unwilling to adapt to it or even who just is a
political dissident against a particular king or noble, that person gets branded as insane.
person is mad.
because they won't conform to the current social structures and they're put into the
earliest islands.
Right.
They're essentially imprisoned at that point in history.
Yeah.
Right.
I mean, it's interesting to think about.
I'm reminded now of, so as you know, from my background in theater, I'm an efficient
some really obscure bits of theatrical history.
And one of them is an, I think it was late, was it late 60s, early 70s show called
Anyone Can Whistle?
Which had the late, now late, Angel Lensbury in it.
So when she died, everyone was like, oh, murder she wrote.
And I'm like, oh, anyone can whistle.
Like it lasted like three days on Broadway.
It was super unpopular.
But anyway, the conceit behind the show is, there's a small town and there's an insane
asylum in town and somehow the gates are left unlocked.
So all the insane people come out and begin to mix with everybody else.
And no one's actually quite sure who's insane and who's not.
Right? Before it was, well, those are the people in there who are imprisoned.
It's interesting to think about that we lock these people up.
That's, it's basically a prison sentence.
And yet, as you said, sometimes they're just sort of political dissidents or whatever,
that there's not necessarily something essentially different about them, you know?
Right, right, and that is
by the way, that's not just something that happened in the medieval period. There have
been various political regimes, even up to the present time, that have used insanity as
an excuse to lock up political dissidents. They haven't actually committed a crime. They
they use insanity as the label to do that.
Sort of the one institution that you have
in medieval Western Europe that kind of preserves some of the earlier
understanding of madness is the king having a fool. Yeah, which is big in, you know,
Shakespeare to bring it back to the era. Yeah, you know, various kinds of fools in Shakespeare's plays.
Some who are they're all kind of funny, but some are mean, some are happy, some are just deeply weird.
Yeah, and yeah, this is the person who because
there a fool, they could kind of say what they want. Yeah. And often they're the truth
teller to the king. He's the one person in the room who can actually say that kind of
stuff. And the king may listen to, although there are various fools throughout history who
you know, cross went too far. Yeah. Right. But the institution is that it's this truth-telling
figure who can kind of say whatever and not get in trouble.
Right, right.
And that's...
sort of a social construction there that preserves that earlier view of the fool, the mad man,
right, of madness. This also became a tool used well into the 20th century, right,
against women, right? So the word hysteria comes from the word for woman.
Yeah, right.
Different woman.
And if you look at you can go online.
and find these the Trans-Alegany in St. Asylum as a good example. And you look at the people in
the 19th and early 20th century who were locked up there. And you'll find a ton of women
and the mental illness for which they were put into this asylum will just be listed as like
woman troubles. Yeah, literally hysteria because I mean, yeah, to be hysterical,
you know, it was decided that had something to do with having a uterus,
You know, like the word his directives.
right? Right. Right.
Have it removed. Yeah. And so the idea there was that any woman who right wasn't willing
to conform to the particular roles of whatever culture they were in that she was supposed
to conform to could end up in an asylum. This is before no fault divorce. It was actually
very difficult for Amanda divorce's wife, but it was actually easier for him to have her
were putting in this island.
Wow.
To get a divorce.
by just alleging things like moodiness.
Right.
Wow.
So, they're right.
But you can see how their madness has become something very different.
It's now become the sociopolitical category that's used to deal with societal dissidents.
You're not part of our societal structures and it's not that that's good anymore.
bad and you're now dangerous. And so you need to be confined. Right. Right. And then this,
this idea sort of segues, there's not like a clear cutoff point, but it segues into the
modern idea of mental illness. Yeah. Right. Where it becomes sort of medicalized. Right. Right.
I mean, for chemical material kinds of causes.
Yeah, and if you look.
at the early quote unquote medical treatments. They're very barbaric, right? The early 20th
century people start doing lobotomies, shock treatment, shock, right? But that's an attempt
to try to at least quasi medicalize this, right? And make it a mental illness. So you have
someone who is a sociopath, they are sick in a way that means that they can't operate within
society. And so they need to be isolated from society. And so instead of a
We have mental hospitals.
Right.
And that becomes medicalized.
But so this shows us, right, looking at this thing that Foucault kind of charts.
It shows us that the whole idea of madness, that whole category,
madness or insanity or whatever term we want to use,
But that's this fluid category.
Right, it doesn't just mean...
refer to one thing throughout history or one type of person. And a person who
would be considered mad in one era might not be in another, or even in different
in different cultures and different places in the same era. What would be considered
bad in one place might not be in another.
And so we have this sort of fluid constant.
concept, but where the fluidity comes in, right, the constant behind all these definitions
is that madness or insanity is always over against the social constructions of that
culture at that time.
So there's a set of social constructions, political, economic, religious, etc., etc., etc.,
That
person is living within in that culture and that society. And the constant
through time is that the people who don't fit within that either because they
can't or they aren't willing to, right? They're the ones who get the label
mad, right? Or insane. And we can when you chart as they've been doing in
modern times charting rates of mental
illness. We can see that that rate of mental illness fluctuates. Yeah, right. Why is it that some
period seem to have more people who are mentally ill than others? Right. And that's because there are
societal shifts with which people are trying to compensate and live.
Let's say, like...
On the one hand, it's, as you said, people trying to compensate, right?
But on the other hand, I would also say, and maybe this is just another angle
from to describe the exact same thing.
As society shifts, people who used to have just been sane are now considered to be insane
because they're not like everybody else.
Right.
And they're not able to adapt and form to the new form.
To the new state of things.
Right.
Yeah.
Which, like, I'm reminded of Brave New World by Alda Suxley,
where you got this character.
of John the Savage, who is the most sort of normal person in the book, and he speaks in Shakespearean
English, which is lovely, because that's where he learned English. And yet he's considered to be a
savage by all these people who are living this very kind of anesthetized pleasure life. You know,
he's the deeply weird one and has to live on some kind of reservation because he's not like them.
Right, right.
And that...
portraying exactly this. Yeah. And this is something that charged across the board, there are parts of the
country now, where there's a huge rise in depression and mental illness and people self-medicating that
illness with drugs and alcohol and things. And when you dig a little deeper, the places where that's
happening our places where there's been some massive shift right in terms of.
of how people are or aren't able to live.
And they're struggling to adapt.
And right, there are people who are just better adapted
to other ways of life.
So there are not a lot of people who are adapted
to thrive spending 40 hours a week in a cubicle farm.
Right. Make me some of it. Yeah. And so when they try to live that way,
the experience, anxiety and all of these other things,
whereas you take some of those people and you have them, you know,
doing farm work and they're fine.
Right. Like in that other context and that other way of life,
they're adapted to it and it suits them. Right.
Um,
And vice versa there's probably somebody who really thrives in a cubicle.
I don't know who that person is, but there might be.
But there can be, right, going even farther than that.
There can be an R and have been historically.
There have been societies and cultures that have become dysfunctional to a point where
they only offer unnatural and inhuman ways of living.
Yeah.
Right.
natural and going against human nature in human and that no human
and can live that way.
Yeah, I mean, and I think probably a lot of people feel,
and there are certainly days when I feel
that our society is moving more and more in that direction.
Yeah.
Yeah, we're just blackpilling everybody tonight. Happy Halloween.
No, we're not.
It's funny. Sometimes people take us a little too literally.
Yeah, like
I don't want to pull the veil back too much here, you know, pay no attention to the man behind the curtain, but just in case, because we did get a couple emails from people from our last Q&A show, where we had, you know, we played a clip, where where someone was, you know, functioning in a deeply pilled way, or if you want to find it.
And they're like, is that the direction your show is going? Like, no, it was a joke. Really, just a joke.
Anyway, yeah.
Yes, but in this case, my unrelenting pessimism is real.
Yeah, right.
But yeah, I mean, but pessimism for the current construct of our society,
not pessimism in terms of no, no, I, I,
the art of the serious.
That's right.
Yeah.
No, I don't think there's any hope in princes and sons of men in whom there's no salvation.
Um, that.
So, but, right, so you could, you could come to that point.
right where you know just the society's so dysfunctional that it will make everyone in it
right yeah dysfunctional and and this is not unrelated right so
it's not unrelated to what we talked about in the last episode
right when when we talked about uh they're being a spirit right that's behind in
and motivating these societies.
One of the things that identifies as we talked about a demonic spirit behind these things is that it is anti-human.
Right, it's destructive. It tears people to pieces.
Right, demons hate and want to destroy humanity. Right. So when we talk about these anti-human constructs,
right, that the societal constructs are built in such a way that it's inhuman, right?
We're also, that's the same, we're talking about the same thing as when we talk about their being this demonic.
that's motivating and driving that society and that culture, right? Just to give an example,
okay? War is demonic. Yep. No human being can naturally thrive and adjust, right? And find salvation
through the desperate quest to
not die to save as many of your friends as you can and to kill an enemy.
Right.
You know, I mean, you people are thrust into that, right, into that in human situation, right?
And try to be heroic.
You can, I mean, there are good things that can happen in the midst of that for sure.
But it's in spite of it.
Right.
That's because you acted in a way that's actually contrary to the spirit of that time.
in place. Right. You don't go and anyone who's actually bent to war will tell you you don't go
there on purpose to try to find salvation. No. No. Right. God can bring good out of any evil. But
that's not right. So you can create these these in human situations and there are these spirits
fine, right? But this points to
the limits that exist on disciplines of psychology and psychoanalysis.
Yeah, because they can't solve the big problem.
They can just try to help you cope.
Right. And this is from either side, right?
Whether we want to talk about it spiritually, like in the last episode, right?
Like psychoanalysts can't do exorcisms.
Right?
they can't drive out that kind of spirit and invoke, right, the Holy Spirit.
This is the difference between confession and therapy.
Yeah, right.
Not that we're saying therapy is bad.
No, but it's a different thing.
But it has limits.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's a different thing.
And it can't get to what confession gets to.
Right.
It's a different thing.
from the other side. If we want to look at
from the side we've been talking about tonight, right? There's this limitation where if I'm doing
counseling, I have a person sitting in front of me who I'm trying to counsel, but I can't change
all of the social structures that that person is forced to interact with on a daily basis, right?
I could only try to help him adapt. And depending on how inhuman those structures are, it may be
impossible.
him to fully adapt or her, right? It may be impossible. So, yes, therapy counseling
useful, but limited. They're useful within a sphere. Yeah, they can't replace the sacraments
and they can't replace some other things that we're going to talk about deeper into the show,
to actually address some of these social structures.
But the key here is that regardless of how the way humans have structured their lives in
these various different ways through human history, that this category of madness is a
category that's used for those who stand outside of that order, however it's been constructed,
However, it exists.
However, it's functioning or dis-
functioning at the time.
You.
All right.
Well, we're going to take a short break.
And when we come back, we're going to talk about one of my favorite figures from the Old Testament,
Nebuchadnezzar.
So we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 8.
558F Radio.
Introducing a new book from Ancient Faith Publishing.
In the whole Council of God, Father Stephen Diyang gives an overview of what the Bible
is and what is its place in the life of an Orthodox Christian, correcting many Protestant
misconceptions along the way.
covered include inspiration, inerrancy. The formation of the biblical
Canon, the various texts and their provenance, the place of Scripture within Orthodox tradition,
and how an Orthodox Christian should read, study and interpret the Bible.
The whole Council of God is now available in paperback, e-book, and audiobook at store.entientfaith.com.
That store.entientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Even the young if you are
a question call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Man I don't know who they got to do the voiceover for that ad but he's great. Such inflection.
You would think so. I mean he does exactly like I would do it. I'm just putting that out
there. Welcome back. I was just.
I was just thinking they're thinking, I don't remember writing any of that, but yeah, that's
what's in the book.
It's true.
Yeah.
Automatic writing.
So yeah, it's the second half, everybody.
We're talking about madness of various sorts.
It's our Halloween episode and you're welcome to give us a ring at a 5.5 AF radio.
That's a 5.5 2, 3, 7, 2, 3, 4, 6.
It's a 5.5 Afraidio.
Afraidio.
I don't know where I'm going to move.
true. Just yeah. I look at that every time and I think that but I'm like no don't say that
because then people will think that there's an eye in there. I don't have to go.
That's a figure now. Yeah. Anyway. Okay. So, Nebuchadnezzar or as it appears in some sources,
Nabu Kodanozor. Yes. It's actually Nabu Koduru Utsur. Right. Which just rolls off the tongue
to be really technical and that's why you get...
the the pedants among us saying actually it should be never could
dress or not nezr nice right yeah so those are people to be
watched carefully and there's an uncle nes you just have to keep an eye on
them in that one episode of Veggie Tales just putting that out
there it's also the ship in the original Matrix movie yeah that's
true wow so yeah Naboo could could do roots are means Naboo who is one of
the main gods.
Yeah.
In that volume life, Nabu, watch over my heir.
My heir, like he, I, R.
Yes.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
Yeah, his dad named him this because he wanted him to survive to adulthood and become king.
Wow.
He's actually a difficult answer to the second.
But his dad was not the first.
was essentially
the founder of the neo-bavilonian empire, which is the Babylonian empire that we see come
and take Judah into exile in the Old Testament. And so we're only talking about like the
sixth century BC, relatively recently by my standards, but we actually have a lot of
stuff a lot of inscriptions including in.
in the things he built in Babylon.
He had his name stamped on every brick.
Wow.
That's so little narcissistic, little little little bit.
There's wow.
Wow.
That just puts a whole other spin on this dude.
And for for old school DC fans
or for people who have watched Black Adam already,
Naboo also a Lord of Horde.
who lives within the helm of Dr. Fade.
There we go.
I'm not a big DC fan.
Just gonna cover the ground.
Cover the ground, do this right.
So, there are a bunch of places where we see
Nebuchadnezzar in the Old Testament.
Daniel is one of the chief ones.
And we're gonna talk about in this second half,
a particular st-
story regarding Nebuchadnezzar that made him the subject of a William Blake painting
that was used, I know, as an image for this episode tonight.
Yep.
I think we also actually used it as the image for last year and then didn't end up getting
to this material.
Right.
That's it.
That's right.
So that's why we recycled the pick.
So that was the cover of the loose leaf expansion.
tonight in the competitive.
Yeah.
Right. And so this particular story about Nebuchadnezzar and Daniel begins
when Nebuchadnezzar has a dream.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So isn't this where he's telling it to Daniel?
Right. Well, yeah, firstly has the dream and he calls in.
He calls in his regular court magician guys.
Better like I got none.
So then finally he calls in Daniel to interpret the drain.
Yeah, okay, so this is from Daniel chapter four.
And depending on if you're reading the Greek Daniel or the Hebrew Daniel, it might be
different verses.
But anyways, technically, technically it's the Aramaic Daniel in chapter four.
Oh, excuse me.
All right, all right.
So here's how it goes.
I, Nebuchadnezzar, was at ease in my house and prospering in my palace.
I saw a dream that made me afraid, because I'd lay in bed the fancies and the visions
of my head.
alarmed me. At last Daniel came in before me, he who is named
Belta Shazar after the name of my God, and in whom is the spirit
of the Holy Gods. And I told him the dream saying, O Belta Shazar,
chief of the magicians, because I know that the spirit of the
Holy Gods is in you, and that no mystery is too difficult for you.
Tell me the visions of my dream that I saw and their interpretation.
The visions of my head as I lay in bed were these. I saw and behold
the tree in the midst of the earth and its height.
It was great. The tree grew and became strong in its top reach to heaven, and it was visible
to the end of the whole earth. Its leaves were beautiful and its fruit abundant, and in
it was food for all. The beasts of the field found shade under it, and the birds of the
heaven lived in its branches, and all flesh was fed from it.
I saw on the visions of my head as I lay in bed, and behold, a watcher, a holy one, came
down from heaven.
proclaimed aloud and said thus. Chop down the
and lop off its branches, strip off its leaves and scatter its fruit, let the beasts flee
from under it and the birds from its branches, but leave the stump of its roots in the earth,
bound with a band of iron and bronze, amid the tender grass of the field. Let him be wet
with the dew of heaven. Let his portion be with the beasts in the grass of the earth, let his
mind be changed from a man's and let a beast's mind be given to him, and let seven periods of time
pass over him. The sentence is by the decree of the watchers.
decision by the word of the Holy ones to the end that the living may know that the most high rules the kingdom of men and
gives it to whom he will and sets over it the lowliness lowliest of men.
So that's pretty self explanatory. Isn't it though?
We do have some fun Easter eggs in there for you know long-time listeners watchers. Yeah, compliment references to watchers. So for example, yeah, and well
And there's this riff.
right right off the bat, right? He calls Daniel by the Babylonian name he was given
Belta Shazar. Yeah, and that bell at the beginning is Bale. Right, right. That's
the sort of Babylonization, the neo-Babalonean Empire of Bale from Seen. That's why he says
called Belta Shazar after the name of my God, right? Right. So that's the God who
of a kid's or is worshiping.
And this is why you may have noticed,
well, you may not have noticed this yet,
unless you're like just super familiar with Daniel.
But if you go and look at a lot of English translations,
when he says to Daniel,
in whom is the spirit of the Holy Gods,
is how we translate it,
but I'll say in whom is the spirit of the Holy God?
And in verse nine also,
they'll have Holy God instead of Holy Gods.
So the word is L.
him right the plural so that could be Elohim being used to refer to God as
it commonly is the Old Testament or that could mean gods the reason why we're
reading it as gods is because here in verse 8 Nebuchadnezzar says you know
that he's named Belta Shazzar after the name of my God right so Nebuchadnezzar's
God is Bell. Right? He doesn't consider the God of the Jews.
God. Yeah. And so he's he's a pagan. Right. So he would at least at this point, right? Yeah.
Maybe not so much of the little bit here, but that's at least right now. He's going to go. He is.
Right. And so he is seeing Daniel when he says in whom is the spirit of the Holy Gods, right?
and he calls up the chief of the magicians.
Right.
He's seeing him as one.
of these people who's touched by the gods, right, who has this special relationship with the gods,
and that potentially at least, for a democonizer, means that he might be able to interpret
these dreams, right, because as we've talked about before on the show, dreams are sort of the
activity of the news, right, so these are seem to be sort of spiritual realities, right, and so
if Daniel has this connection with these.
with these spiritual beings, they are more of where of these spiritual realities
than can explain them and serve as a guide to them.
That's how people can nezzarous thinking about this.
And so he has this vision that of this tree that grows tall and strong and huge
and fills the whole earth, right?
And, right, which...
Well, we'll just summarize it now. We'll get to the interpretation of the second.
Right. Fill us a hole earth. And then a watcher, right, as Father Andrew mentioned, for
all you book of ENIC fans, right, the term watcher to refer to a certain class of holy
ones, a certain class of angelic beings. Here it is in the canonical scriptures. We're
not making this up, even if you're not Ethiopian. Right. So.
And it's one of them who comes and announces that there is this sentence, there's this decree that this tree is going to be chopped down, right?
But the stump is not going to be removed.
And then there's kind of a mixing of the metaphor because the tree is not going to have a man's mind. Apparently there's a tree with a man's mind.
And now it's going to have a beast's mind.
Yeah, it just sort of flips at that point.
Yeah.
it's tree it it and then it's let him be wet with the do of heaven, let his
portion be with the beasts. Yeah, let his mind be changed. Yeah, yeah. So, and the
last thing to note is that at the end, right, this sentence is the decree, this
is the decree of the watchers, the decision by the word of the holy ones, to the
end of that is in order that so that the living, all the living, right, on
on earth, people on earth.
May know that.
the most high rules the Kingdom of Men and gives it to whom he will and sets over at the
loliest of men.
So this decision is presented as having been taken by the Divine Council.
It's not just this angel does not just come in and out, here's what God says.
But he says, this is the decree of the Council, obviously over which God presides.
The purpose of this decree makes it very clear.
that the most high God who presides in that counsel is above the rest of it. Right? Right.
Let's go to show who's in charge. So then Daniel is then able to interpret this dream. Yeah. Okay.
So continuing on this begins with well in some versions verse 19.
Then Daniel, whose name
was Belta Shazar was dismayed for a while, and his thoughts alarmed him.
The king answered and said, Belta Shazar, let not the dream or the interpretation alarm
you.
Belta Shazar answered and said, My Lord, may the dream be for those who hate you and
its interpretation for your enemies.
The tree you saw which grew and became strong so that its top reached to heaven, and it
was visible to the end of the whole earth whose leaves were beautiful and its fruit abundant,
and in which food was for all, under which beasts to the field found shade and in whose branches
the birds till heavens live.
And it is you, O King, who have grown and become strong.
Your greatness has grown and reaches to heaven, and your dominion to the ends of the earth.
And because the King saw Watcher, a holy one, coming down from heaven, this is the interpretation
O King, it is a decree of the most high which has come upon my Lord the King, that you shall
be driven from among men, and your dwelling shall be with the beasts of the field.
You should be made to eat grass like an ox, and you shall be wet with the dew of heaven.
seven periods of time shall pass over you till you know that the most high rules the kingdom
of men and gives it to whom he will. And as it was commanded to leave the stump of the roots
of the tree, your kingdom shall be confirmed for you from the time that you know that heaven
rules. Therefore, King, let my counsel be acceptable to you, break off your sins by practicing
righteousness and your niceties by showing mercy to the oppressed, that there may perhaps be a
lengthening of your prosperity.
Yeah, so he gets this offer of, you know, potential for repentance at the end, you know,
do what you're supposed to do.
Right.
So Daniel at first doesn't want to tell him, right?
Because as we mentioned, sometimes the fool goes too far.
Right.
Yeah.
And he doesn't know how Devakites is going to react.
But he says, you know, like, I hope this is actually about your enemies, but it's not.
Yeah.
But it's kind of about you.
And so, right, this is him.
He's grown strong.
He's extended his power through the Neobablonian Empire
over the whole world.
But, right, he needs to learn something.
Right, he needs to learn something.
He needs to learn that it is the most high god
who rules over the world.
And who?
gives authority within it, the person who he wants to have it.
And that's why he needs to learn that his verse 26 says,
heaven rules, not him, right?
And in order for him to learn that,
he is going to have this experience
of being driven from men.
Not only is he not gonna occupy this position atop, right?
The Babylonian empire atop the social structures of his time.
but he is going to
be driven out from them and live like an animal. But as you mentioned, Daniel concludes by saying,
hey, this is this is the sentence. But you know what, if if you were to repent now and learn this
lesson now, then none of this would have to happen. But it's not when that's not the way it went down.
Yeah, right. Right. Because because you get, you know, this is the next thing, right? The next
First, all this came upon Kegnebikenezu.
and skipping ahead a few verses.
Immediately, the word was fulfilled against Nebuchadnezzar.
He was driven from among men and ate grass like an ox,
and his body was wet with the dew of heaven
till his hair grew as long as eagle's feathers
and his nails were like birds' claws.
Which, if you look at that William Blake painting
of Nebuchadnezzar, that's exactly what's depicted.
It's this kind of almost werewolf sort of image.
The way we imagine a werewolf, anyway.
Right, right.
And so we have to remember, this is the neo-Babalonean empire, right?
This is our latest and in some ways last really, instantiation of Mesopotamian culture,
self-consciously harkening back to the original Babylonian empire, right, of Hammurabi and
the Amaru.
This is his self-concept.
And so essentially, he goes from...
being able to see himself as Gilgamesh, this God king, this divine king, who in some way stands
over and above the social order with the other gods as his peers to being more like Enkidu,
to being this wild man out in the wilderness. Through this encounter he has, with God mediated through
these angelic beings.
And
So not only is the most high god, not his peer, right?
But even the watchers who pronounce this judgment are not his peers.
Even the adjellic beings, right?
And so he, from his perspective, the way the Assyrian and Babylonian empires essentially
worked, it wasn't...
they didn't have, but...
a federal government, right? Then like local governments of the different city states, right?
Because they didn't have the communication abilities to do that.
Right. Right. So you still had kings in these different city states. Those kings were just
vassals of the emperor, of the the high king of so in this case of Nebuchadnezzar.
Nebuchadnezzar when he made that king of Vassal,
which would happen in one of two ways.
Either he'd conquer a city,
right, or be about to conquer a city,
and the king would cut a deal to become his Vassal,
or he'd conquer a city, kill the current king
and install a Vassal.
Yeah, climb.
And the new king.
And when he did that, he would issue them a covenant,
right, he would cut them a covenant and say,
hey, I'm the king, you're now my Vassal, right.
Here's what I-
I will do for you, right?
In terms of someone attacks you,
I will bring my army to defend the city, et cetera, et cetera.
Here's what you're gonna do for me
in terms of taxes, in terms of tribute, whatever else.
Yeah.
So how many soldiers you're gonna field for my army?
And then here are the consequences
if you break this, right?
Here's what I'm gonna do to you
if you don't obey the agreement I've just given you, right?
So it's not a contract, it's not a mutual agreement.
It's given by the Sussaron to the Vassal.
And so what God is here showing Nebuchadnezzar
is that even though he's the king, he's the emperor,
he's the Sussaron, he's the high king,
he is at best a Vassal of God most high.
And there will be consequences
if he does not live up to the responsibilities
that he has as God's Rassel.
Yep, yep, then this is the consequence he becomes a beastman
Right, but this is not last forever. Yes, no, it doesn't you know
So yeah starting with verse 34 again depending on which version you're looking at
At the end of the days I
Nebuchadnezzar lifted my eyes to heaven and my reason returned to me and I blessed the most high and praised and honored him who
lives.
forever, for his dominion is an everlasting dominion, and his kingdom endures from generation
to generation.
All the inhabitants of the earth are counted as nothing, and he does, according to his
will, among the host of heaven and among the inhabitants of the earth.
And none can stay his hand or stay to him what have you done.
At the same time my reason returned to me, and for the glory of my kingdom, my majesty and
splendor returned to me.
My counselors and my lords sought me and I was established in my kingdom.
more greatness was added to me. Now, I, Nebuchadnezzar, praise and extol and honor the King of Heaven
for all his works are right and his ways are just and those who walk and pride he is able to humble.
The thing especially about that last line is, I mean, that almost sounds like he'd be right out of the
Psalms, right? That's the way he talks now. He talks like the Psalms. Yeah. Yeah. And so who knows
then the age to come if we will.
or never can this are there.
Huh.
Don't go naming any churches after him just yet.
Yeah, no.
I'm not authorized to tell you to do that anyway.
It's about my pay grade, but just who knows?
But,
notice of things here that there has been a profound shift
in his thinking.
Yeah.
Right.
Why is there all this about the most high that he lives forever?
His dominion is an everlasting dominion.
His kingdom endures from generation to generation, right?
Well, because Babylonian, Mesopotamian religion,
there had been a series of succession myths.
Yeah, right.
Right.
This is one of these things that is a mark of the most high God
according to the Bible about how He's different
from all other spiritual beings.
you know, who among the gods?
is like unto the hour Lord. Right. Right. And so the gods he used to worship, right? Nabu,
Marduk, right. Bell, right? These are gods who were who were born and who die. Yeah. I think it's worth
underlining once again that if you, you know, sometimes when people critique Christianity, they sort of
treat it like it's basically saying the same things about its God that all the other religions say
about their gods. But if you...
actually look at what those religions say about their gods. It's not on the same level.
Like, just take what they say about their own religion, you know, sitting aside the question
of whether the claims are true or false. They don't actually make those kinds of claims about
their gods, that they're from everlasting, that they're all powerful, that they're, you know,
that's just not a thing, just not even there. No paganism does that.
Right, and not only were they born and can they die.
but whatever rule, whatever dominion, whatever kingdoms they have come into being at a certain point and can fall. Right.
And other gods. Right.
And so that's why he goes so far in verse 35 to say he does according to his will, not just among the inhabitants of the earth, not just among humans, but among the host of heaven.
Yeah, he's in charge amongst the gods.
So, you think there is as much difference between the most high God and the God.
as there is between the gods and humans effectively.
Right?
So he's had a profound shift here.
Yeah.
Right?
And he's come to understand exactly
the lesson he was supposed to understand.
Right?
That his kingdom and any power he has is delegated.
And temporal, right?
like the whole world of his empire.
is temporary, it's constructed and it's going to fall apart.
Right. Right.
And so what's happened here in terms of our overarching theme that we're talking about tonight.
Right. Because this is, you know, Nebuchadnezzar is driven mad.
Right. In order to learn this lesson.
And that is that he is removed for a time from this entire social construction.
of the Babylonian Empire, right?
From the whole cultural history of it,
the cycle of feasts, the gods, all of that.
He's removed from it.
He's living as not even a human,
let alone as a Babylonian, right?
He's completely removed from that.
And what that allows is for him to be reoriented
to reality, to the reality of the cosmos, right?
To the reality of God's creation,
the reality of his human name.
nature and to come to really understand his place in the creation and in the
cosmic order and in cosmic justice. And then once he understands that, right, he
can re, he in this case reenters those structures, but in a different way. Right. And in a
way that who knows maybe if he'd lived longer would have been transformative to
those structures but he didn't live that long after this.
And his son was a near-to-well.
So he had a fail son as many great kings do.
But this shows he had to be removed from it in order to be reoriented and be able to
approach it from another angle in a different way with a new wisdom and a new perspective.
Right.
Alright, well, that...
We're going to go ahead and take our second break and we'll be right back with the third
half of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Hi, I'm John Maddick, CEO.
of Ancient Faith Ministries.
With my wife and I started Ancient Faith Radio back in 2004, we did so with the understanding
that the success and growth of this fledging ministry would be entirely dependent on the
will of God as expressed through the generous support of its listeners.
As the station moved from our back porch to our basement to the state of the art studio
in which it currently resides, we have never wavered from this commitment to keeping AFR
a free resource for...
orthodox Christians, depending only on listener contributions for its continued existence.
We do not have gated content in ancient faith radio requiring some sort of subscription
fee.
Nor do we look to make a profit from the content we provide.
That said, it does take a great deal of money for AFR to maintain its high standard of quality
and keep up with the ever-changing world of Internet radio.
And as always, our ability to do so is so-
reliant on you, the Lucitor. Would you consider becoming a participant in the
work of Ancient Faith Radio, partnering with us to bring the Orthodox Christian
faith to the modern world, donate today by going to ancientfaith.com and
clicking on Donate in the upper right-hand corner, thanks in advance for your
generosity.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Thanks, boys of Steve.
We're back now with a third half of Lord of Spirits.
We're talking about, you know,
I like the ragtime piano in that one.
And I know, that was a little,
I felt like specific.
I don't know what it was about to happen.
Right?
I
I never realized it by think John Madness is kind of a Paul Newman type.
Huh? Huh?
I'm not to think about that word for a while.
I think it might be true though.
Just dwell on that a little bit.
Now suddenly I'm seeing him in cool hand Luke.
Yeah.
No man can eat 58.
Some men you just can't.
Anyway.
Yes.
So we're talking about divine madness.
Actually, several different kinds of madness.
and we just talked about...
Nebuchadnezzar or Nebuchadnezzar or Nebuchadnezzar or the longer version you said earlier.
Nebuchadnezzar. There we go. That would be hard to put on a license plate.
I'm just, you know, for PMO states at least, yes. Yes, right. Yeah. The new
about Lonely and Empire that's available on your free license plate. But...
For the record, we're not talking about the all I wanted was a Pepsi, just one Pepsi
and she wouldn't give it to me.
type of madness.
Even though that will result in you being put in an institution.
That's an old, old, old pack.
So in this act, there are five people who got that, but those are my people.
It's right.
Call in, let us know.
We don't need a bunch of calls that are just, I got that one.
I caught that reference.
Quick, send us Captain America Gifts.
We know what that is.
Yes, that is...
Yes, right. Right. So yes, this is our Halloween episode. So we always talk about crazy stuff on Halloween or Halloween episode and indeed this time we're talking about craziness itself.
So yeah, yeah. Yeah. What is the difference between madness and divine madness, mental illness, demonic possession like is there a way to test to see, you know, what somebody's got.
God then he couldn't even call the
Dr. the exorcist in St. Asylum, I mean, what do you know?
Right.
And these questions come up on all sides.
So in our culture, as we were talking about earlier in the first half, we now,
we talk about mental illness and we see this in sort of medical terms.
And so this raises and biomedical.
we mean at least we're trying to be scientific in our approach to it, right?
And sometimes we are, sometimes maybe not so much still, but we're trying.
And so this comes up on the one hand, right?
How do you tell someone who is the contemporary equivalent of a fool for Christ in the Christian tradition
from someone who is mentally ill?
Right.
Because I've encountered people.
Yeah, it's good to say.
I've encountered someone who said they had a vision of me before they met me.
I've been, you know, it's a priestess happens, right?
So you encounter people who say they've had visions, say they've had experiences.
Yeah, my favorite maybe, I don't know if that's the right word.
I mean, no disrespect.
When I was in seminary, you might have had to do this two.
I don't remember part of what we did as part of our seminary study was prison ministry.
And there was a psych ward as part of the ministry.
And there was one guy, I can't remember his name now,
but he used to say to the priest who had come and visit,
he would say, now look, Father, I'm Jesus Christ.
And you are my servant.
And so I have some things for you to do.
And as far as we knew, this guy truly believed
what he was saying.
I mean, he would not be the first person.
to claim to be Jesus in the modern period.
I think we have 100 of those every week, it seems like.
Right, right.
So we accept as Orthodox Christians that there is such a thing
as a fool for Christ.
Also, there are a lot of people who might present themselves
in religious terms, but who we would ultimately say
are mentally ill.
This is not wisdom coming from God, but this is a person
who's mentally ill. Who needs?
certain types of help and assistance, right?
And then on the other side, right on the other side you have because
our contemporary society we think about mental illness in this medicalized, right and and
Scientized way who will say for example that the examples of demonic possession in the Bible even are just mental illness
Yeah, right and and
and ancient people were just primitive and dumb
and didn't understand the concept of mental illness.
And so...
He doesn't need an exorcism.
He needs a prescription.
Right.
And so how do you distinguish between someone who is mentally ill, someone who is demon
possessed or a demonized person?
Right?
Where is the problem, something that's going to be solved by an exorcism and repentance?
Where is it?
I mean, repentance is always good.
But where is it?
Where do we not need an exorcism and we just need sort of repentance and medication or
What happened?
right? You just want therapy. Talk it out. So within this, right, mental illness is sort
of the broader category, right? Because mental illness is essentially the way we now talk
about what used to be called insanity, what before that was called madness, right? So it's
this broader category that includes lots of different phenomena, lots of different things,
Right, and this is like we started out.
with people who for whatever reason can't or won't function within or flourish within
society. And we're with no comment about the origin of that. Like it's just they can't
or won't or whatever. For a variety of reasons. Yeah. There's lots of
unableable reasons. Unable to flourish. If it's severe, they can't even function. Right.
In society, the way it's currently ordered. Right. And so that we're using that as the
broad category.
Right. And so when we talk about someone who's a fool for Christ or a holy fool, right, we're talking about a person who's not functioning within society as presently ordered due to an experience of God, due to an experience an encounter they've had with God, which is set them outside of those societal structures so that they can sort of testify to it. Right. We'll get into that more in a minute.
Thank you.
And when we talk about a person, we're talking about a person who's not functioning within
society due to being controlled by an inhuman and or anti-human spiritual force.
Yeah, so they've been touched by something else that's not God that is now controlling
them.
So it's not even just having one expo
It's an ongoing thing.
Right, and that's why they're outside, right? So there could be any number of causes for someone being outside and unable to function within the social order
two of those
what we would call someone being a fool for Christ
Or someone being demonically possessed and then there are a whole array of others that fall into that brought that would fall into the category of mental illness
Yeah, right
so
We talked previously in our...
episode about prophets and prophecy. We talked a little bit about this idea of the Holy
Fool or the Fool for Christ because some of those characteristics we see in various old
Testament prophets. So these people have an encounter with God, this prophetic call, and
then based on that they are removed from sort of society. So St. Elias, the prophet
Elijah right out.
out in the wilderness.
St. John the Forerunner, likewise, taking up his lifestyle.
Ezekiel has visions and then wanders around naked.
Basically, we're going to get close.
Or like, Hosea with his marriage.
That's deeply weird, deeply weird in that society.
Right.
And so they're sort of transgressing societal norms.
They're not living within these societal structures.
But the reason they're
doing it is that this experience they've had with God has set them outside of it so that
they can come and then testify to it.
Right.
They can corrective character that's going on.
They have to stand outside it to critique it, to question it, right, to point out where
it's gone wrong.
And so when it comes to someone who might present themselves as a fool for Christ or might
it has
some attributes that might cause you to wonder that.
If someone is presenting in that way,
but the wisdom they're claiming to have from God,
the testimony they're claiming to give,
is not of a sort of consistent character, right?
Is not prophetic, or is not people to repentance.
Right, bringing people to friends,
applying the message of God, right?
And then that would be.
case where we say, okay, this person is not functioning as a fool for Christ. This is a mentally ill person.
Right. Say Cyril Mosque has another famous holy fool, right, who lived naked in Russia
in the streets for several years and didn't die. So that was a sign of something.
Yeah. Because it gets very, very cold. And one episode went and confronted Ivan the terrible
All the big slam of meat.
It was not it wasn't that basil the fool for Christ isn't that was basil the fool Christ right right that's a basil
Hall all this slab of meat before
I have a terrible threw it in front of and said take an eat. He said I can't it. It's lent
He said then why do you feast on the blood of men right? Yeah
So he is fulfilling this prophetic role
Yeah, right he's the only one who can dare call this r2 repentance
That's right.
And so the odd behavior, the quote-unquote crazy behavior that he's engaging in, right?
We can see the purpose behind it.
And so we can understand this person as a full-for-Christ.
Right.
So to use an archetypal example for a demoniac, archetypal, not only because of the
length of the story but also because of the number
of times we read it every year, the Orthodox Church for some reason.
Two or three on Sundays.
Yeah.
Is the story of the gathering or garrison, uh, demoniac?
The one with the pigs, everybody.
Right.
With Legion, the devil ham, that whole story.
That's right.
Um, I hope everybody made that joke or heard that joke this past Sunday.
That is the traditional dad joke.
Yeah.
For, uh, and since we're called father is Orthodox priest, we have to make that joke.
We're calling it a three-on-the-job.
Statue it's canonical.
So the, this demoniac, when we first encounter him, has been removed from society, right?
He's living in the tombs naked, right?
Riding around living like an animal, right?
But there's no sort of testimony coming from him to the society at large.
No.
He's menacing the local people, right?
In various ways.
And it's important to note here,
that people don't just end up demon possessed
like this by accident one day.
Yeah, it's not like they're walking down the road
and a demon sneaks up on them
and slithers into their brain, takes control of them.
Like you don't accidentally get demon possessed.
Right, or they played with a Weechy board once at a slumber party. Right. Right.
Not that that's a good thing to do. Yeah, that's not instantly going to get you possessed by a
thousand demons. Right. Right. And have you running naked in the tombs? No, this is this is
this is it's it's just like you know it's the opposite effect of if you
if you live a holy life then you become a pure of the angels and you function like the angels.
If you live an evil life and like
of the evil, then you become like the demons and you are not in the divine council.
You're in whatever the opposite of that is.
You're in the infernal, well, it's not a council.
The infernal mob.
Yeah.
And so this is something that happened to him.
He ended up at this state over a long period of time.
Yeah.
Right.
of living in more and more demonic way.
And...
that actually makes this a very hopeful story.
Because it means that if he was not too far gone
for Christ to come and heal him,
then pretty much nobody else is too far gone either.
Right.
But note here that once the demons are cast out,
and they go to the pigs and the pigs jump
No.
Christ doesn't reintegrate this man into his Gentile Galilean society. We know it's Gentiles
because they're hurting pigs. Right. Right. He doesn't say, well, good. Now you can go get a job
and become a taxpayer in Galilean. Right. Go find yourself a wife, have a couple of kids, settle down.
right. The Galilean dream. Right. So this is it.
Christ like reintegrating this person into society. He doesn't want to reintegrate into society, right?
He begs Christ to go with him and become a disciple. Yeah. Yeah. To leave all that behind and go
become a disciple. Christ instead turns them into an apostle. He sends them. He says, you need to stay
here and you need to tell everyone. Yeah. What happened? Everybody. What God has done for you.
It's interesting. I mean, this is one of the, there's moments where where Christ says, now, don't tell
anybody?
but this is one where he says, now go and tell.
Right.
And so he now has this apostolic and prophetic mission
that begins with what?
With his encounter with God.
Yeah.
In the person of Jesus Christ.
And so now he becomes set apart from society
in the opposite way.
Mm-hmm.
So now he can go and testify to that Gentile Galilean
society about who Christ is.
Yeah, so instead of being down to that.
a full will, he's a holy full now.
Right. Right.
And so this connection to experience
is can also be true in a lot of cases
with other broader types of mental illness.
Right.
Where experiences in life, ongoing experiences in life,
trauma, right, these kinds of things in life
can change a person.
in such a way that they're no longer able to adapt to the social structures that they
might have previously felt at home in.
Yeah.
I mean, like a really good example.
You know, we brought up warfare earlier.
People come home with PTSD.
Sometimes they can, the trauma, you know, they can sometimes adapt and sometimes they can't.
They sometimes they just come back and they are never the same.
Right.
So um.
When a big part of why this understanding is important,
in terms of the social order and whether or not we can and will and should,
adapt to it is that there are a number of different ways in which the phrase,
the world, right, is used in Scripture.
But one of those ways refers to the world all
almost as this sort of oppressive entity, like the world, the flesh, and the devil.
Right.
And there's a way of reading that, if you're say, a gnostic or a Puritan, in which that
means the things in the world, the material world.
Yeah.
And that's not how it's in the Scripture.
And that's why, for instance, Jesus says he came not to condemn the world.
but to save it. That's a different usage of the world.
Right. Right. And so this understanding of the world is about the social order that
humans construct in the world. Right. Never forget.
Cane built the first city. Yeah. First police is him. Right. It's about
these pathological orders that we can
in the world. Right? And by those being the social constructs in the world, there is an innate
pressure on every one of us to conform to that. Why? Well, it's not fun being unable to function and
unable to flourish in the world you live in. Right. So for us in
contemporary society, most of the people.
listening to this, right? We have to find a way to make enough money to buy the goods and services
we need to shelter ourselves, clothe ourselves, feed ourselves, right? We have to find a way to
function within the order as it exists now to survive within it, let alone flourish, right?
Right. Let alone try to work toward our salvation and do these other things. So there's always this
this pressure to conform, because conformity, at least in theory,
right, makes life within that order easier, right? It might not make human flourishing easier,
but it makes life in that order easier, right? And so the world has always been
this force, just like it was for Nebuchadnezzar, right? Just as it was for the first Christians in
the pagan Roman Empire who faced all this pressure to participate in the festivals,
to make this sacrifice.
is so they could be in a trade guilt to be good Romans. And then everything would get easier.
This exists for Christians today who live in Islamic countries or who live in countries with
some kind of tyrannical social order that's and expressly anti-Christian. If you just become a good
citizen, right? Whatever this is, you just convert if you just shift if you just
stop being a Christian so much.
Yeah, just be normal.
Everything will go easier for you.
Yeah.
Right?
Everything will go easy for you.
And that's what the world is.
The world is that set of social structures
that are constantly,
a temptation, a seduction,
right, this force, this enemy of us finding our salvation.
Yeah.
and this connects of course directly with what we were talking about.
the last episode because what animates that sense of the world is demonic spirit.
Right. That's what's animating that order. Yeah. The spirit of the age is not the Holy Spirit.
Right. The spirit of the age to come is the Holy Spirit. But not this present evil age.
Yep, yep.
Yeah, so I mean, you know that...
The goal of being Christian then is not to be a good citizen.
It's, you know, of the world.
It's to be a good citizen of the kingdom of Christ, which doesn't mean you need to be a menace to society.
But, but that you know, oh, I can make the, well, actually that's not that an obscure reference, but...
No, I was just saying I want to be a menace.
Oh!
No, you may not.
Yeah, it's not to be a menace, you know, a menace to society, but rather to bring the order
of God into it, right?
So yeah, be a good citizen of Christ's kingdom, which can make you look crazy to the world
at times.
So well, to wrap up, there was a conversation I was privy to recently.
you were there two fathers to even which is
Recently our diocesan clergy had our annual what's called clergy synaxis and
Father Stephen was our speaker and
One of the features of the gathering is always conversations with our bishop which is always great and
You know someone brought up to him and ask him to speak about something that's a very controversial subject in our time, right and
And I won't get into what it is exactly because...
because that's a whole other can of worms.
But it's a moral issue.
It's an anthropology issue.
I'll just put it that way.
And it was interesting to watch him,
like he didn't have a prepared statement.
By no means does the bishop think or say or teach anything
that's out of step with Orthodox tradition
with regards to this issue?
Not at all.
But it was interesting to hear him sort of think out loud
how he wanted to say what he was going to say.
He didn't ever.
prepared statement. And actually I think my bishop almost never has a prepared statement.
In a couple of times, I know he's walked in with one. He said something else entirely because
that's just what he wanted to say. But in any event, it was interesting to listen to what he said
because there was one point where his first reaction was almost like, well, that's just kind of
just a distraction. And certainly understanding that people who are...
dealing with this issue and maybe suffering from it, that they need pastoral care. Right?
Because another thing he said, he says, well, this is just a matter of sin. And we know what to do
about sin. We repent. You know, that's what we do about sin. Right? So you teach repentance. You
got to teach it with love, apply it in a very beautiful pastoral way. But there was one point where
where he said, and this is where he kind of ended up.
He said, you know, if you really are committed.
to the life of the church, especially to the life of prayer and worship.
But the whole matrix of what it is that we do as Orthodox Christians, the prayer, the
fasting, the om's giving, the learning, the active love for our family and for our neighbor,
for our fellow parishioners, etc.
He said, if you really are doing that and the more that you do that, you actually
discover that these questions, these very controversial issues of our time, that not only will
they not control you, and this is what he said, they actually become invisible. Now, by
that he didn't mean you get to ignore what's going on in the world. That's not what he
meant. But what he meant was that your perspective changes so much, because, and this is my interpretation
everybody said my sort of paraphernalist.
phrase of it, you realize the story you're really in. You know? And when you know that the
real story of what's going on in the world is a matter of Christ's rescue of us from these
demonic influences, and you realize that the real battle is a spiritual battle, then those are
the tools that you begin to apply in every situation. And so it's not that the, the not that people
get tight.
into or sometimes tie themselves up and do as a result of a lot of the big controversies
of our day, it's not that we look and just say, oh, well, just, you know, come on, shape up,
just stop it. You know, that's not what that's not what he meant at all. But rather there's
a sense that you begin to see those things in true perspective. And when you, what you
then bring to them is the wholeness and the beauty and the glory and the sanity, the
sanity of God right you know just like you know
I know a lot of people listen to this show.
Our parents, I'm a parent.
And your kids will often act in ways that seem kind of nuts.
You know, sometimes they just completely lose it.
And it's really easy to get caught up in their craziness,
to become obsessed with it.
But if you keep your perspective
and you watch your child melting down in front of you,
Number one, you don't stop.
loving them and you don't turn towards them not caring about what's going on with them.
You care because they're suffering clearly, even when they're losing their minds in a
destructive way.
They're suffering, absolutely.
But you also have the perspective to know that it's possible to come out of that.
That it's possible for that not to be the way that you function anymore.
possible to become sane. Right?
And I thought that was what was so beautiful about what the Bishop said is, you know, he
was really speaking as a father to children, a father to fathers of children also, and
that the way of having sanity, the way of really becoming whole, is to conform ourselves to
the kingdom of God.
And the more that we do that, then we're able to bring that to other people.
And so he always, one of his big sayings, he always says is, you know, a priest should spend, you know,
the table that should concern the priest the most is the altar table, not the desk in his office.
And it's true. It's absolutely true. But that's not true, just a priest's, right? It's true for all
of us. And when we bring ourselves into that ordered way of living, which is the way that God has given
this in his body, the church. When we
conform ourselves, you know, connecting back to our previous episode to what the Holy Spirit
is leading us to do by being obedient to the commandments, by doing all these things that
we know to do.
All the things that you're pleased to ask you to do that maybe you don't do so much.
Then we are able, number one, we will, as a result, kind of be taken outside of society,
like we've been talking about, we'll be holy fools on some level.
But more important.
certainly, we will be oriented to the life of the world to come. We'll be oriented to the
kingdom of God. It's not just in the future, but it's also breaking into this moment. And
so I just wanted to pass on that very, very beautiful word that he gave us. Although I
probably said in a thousand more words than he ever would have. He's pretty to the point
of the way that he talks.
Father Stephen, what's your final comments for this evening?
So I'm going the opposite tack.
All right.
I'm going straight after, as my example,
a hot button social issue in cancellation attempt number four.
So I wanna dig a little deeper in terms of where we ended.
And this is ultimately hopefully going to be
to get past the whole black pill pessimism thing
to something at least.
potentially positive for us. And that is, we have to recognize the fact that
what's the right word to use. So the church, as she stands before Christ, is holy and
blameless and pure. Not so at least in the present time are individual Christian communities
in which we live, right?
or at least which we visit, which is part of the problem I'll come back to here in a minute.
And in many ways, this is especially true, I think, for us who live in countries where there is not a sense of antithesis between what we were just calling the world, the culture.
the political realities, the economic realities, right?
The social constructions in which we live.
When we're in a country where there's not a sense
of antithesis between that and Christianity,
we've become especially prone
to our Christian communities being co-opted
by those social constructions
and used as a means to promote
conformity to them, right?
Used as a way to make people good citizens, right?
To make people good people.
And this has been so thorough going, for example,
in some English-speaking countries,
that the word Christian now is essentially
an adjective that means proper or good, right?
Or put together, right?
means the equivalent of cl-
cut, right? Your Christian name is your proper name, right? And this is a massive problem
for everyone who is attempting to work out their salvation in a Christian community. When
the Christian community itself rather than providing respite in a different direction
from conformity to the world is actually being used as a tool for conformity to the world.
And as I mentioned, I'm now going to...
pick a completely non-controversial example, I'm going to talk about marriage and same-sex
marriage as an example.
So on one hand, right, on one hand, we have what is currently called.
And again, I primarily always have to speak for the United States because that's where
I live.
That's what I'm most familiar with.
We have communities where the current version of conservatism has taken rain.
I say current
because today's conservative is always yesterday's liberal.
And last week's radical, right?
So the position that's being conserved in any given point in time is usually a fairly late position
that would have been radical not that long before.
But so for example, we have the current conservative position where it's taken hold in Christian communities
which has taken the nuclear family.
I've talked about this before on this show,
but they're taking the nuclear family,
which is sort of the last surviving bear fossilized
remnant of what family once was,
the extended family, the clan, right?
The people group, right?
This last remaining little vestige
and has made that now the end all in Biel.
And as is the tendency with conservatism,
whatever the current social structures are,
are thought to be number one natural,
this just conforms to nature,
and to be essentially eternal.
This is the way it's always been.
You're hard pressed to find a lot of nuclear families
in the Bible, but I digress.
And so it is purely on the nuclear family.
Well, what does that do?
Well, that makes unmarried people
in those Christian communities feel like
second class citizens.
That makes them feel even more isolated and alone than they might already do because they don't have a partner to share their life with.
That makes part of the nuclear families having children so that makes couples who are unable to have children feel ostracized and they're looked at with suspicion.
Sometimes outright called selfish.
And this dysfunction, right, within the Christian community, is not helping any of these people
flourish as human.
or find salvation.
But a foreign, cultural view has come in and taken hold.
And you don't find anything better on what we still in the United States at least call the other side,
where we have the more progressive or liberal or however we want to inadequately use terms.
terms. And I think we see this most clearly when we come to the issue of...
same-sex marriage. Because those and there are even a few of these folks in the
Orthodox Church, I won't name names. Most of people isn't even probably know who I'm
talking about, who see same-sex marriage as something that that should happen
within their local Orthodox Christian communities. And the way they portray it is
they will say, well, we need to accept.
people who identify as homosexual who want to be in monogamous lifelong
relationships with the part. But what's going on here? Right? Because the whole
basis for monogamous lifelong marriage. Right? If we want to go with the Bible,
It's that as Christ said, God created humanity, male and female.
and they become one flesh.
And there's at least the potential there to produce children.
So biblically, that's the basis for monogamous marriage.
And if we don't want to go biblically,
because some of those same folks aren't so big on
literal interpretations of the Bible,
we could just go at this from a biological and zoological perspective.
Higher mammals mate for life.
biologically male and female.
mammals made for life and raised children. So that's the whole basis for it. So why then would
someone who wants to present themselves as in some way progressive or radical argue that the answer
for a person who because they experience same sex desires, homosexual desires is outside of
of the current social order.
Why would...
they think that the answer for that is to parent this sort of nuclear family structure,
this sort of monogamous marriage structure, right?
Because they're not actually challenging the structure.
It's not radical at all.
It's actually kind of reactionary.
They're trying to just widen the category enough that we can squeeze some more people into
it.
We can get some more people to conform, right?
questioning
What's being held is an ideal and it's not because these people care about these folks who identify as homosexual. They don't care about them at all.
But they want to preserve the social constructions that they personally are beneficiaries of and they want to assuage their own personal neurotic guilt at benefiting from them by diversifying them or making them more inclusive.
So they want to pry it open just a little.
These same folks, these are the folks who don't want to talk about the military and industrial
complex.
They just want to diversify the army, and then everything will be cool.
So that's not a solution either.
Both of these quote-unquote sides are just trying to preserve a status quo and could form
more people to the world and use Christian communities as a way to do that.
as a way to funnel people into it.
So what's the alternative?
This is the good news part, right?
Is that we do have an alternative, right, as Christians.
As Christians, we do not have to conform
to any of the social structures in this world.
We can live and be in the world
in a completely different way in Christ.
And so we can take our Christian communities, our parishes,
right?
and we can transform them.
from a place that's visited a couple times a week, a venue for worship, right, for a certain type of activity.
We can transform them into actual communities.
Into communities where we can create a family structure, a new family structure in Christ that is part of the household of God.
say Paul talks about this all the time.
That goes beyond the nuclear family
that's a result of the industrial.
or the diversified nuclear family
that's the weird, compromised position.
But that is a social unit and a family
that has a place for unmarried people
and a role for them in our community
that has a place for couples
who for whatever reason don't have children.
That has a place for married couples
that do have to.
that is a place where we all can be freed from.
These and all the other ideas and concepts and constructs in our society
that are preventing us from drawing closer to Christ,
that are trying to get us to conform to them instead of to Christ,
where we can be free to flourish and come to know Jesus ever more deeply.
and will know we're being successful.
in doing this. We'll know that we really have this type of community, not just when everybody thinks we're weird.
That'll be step one. Right? Say Peter says we should be like aliens and strangers in the world, not at home.
But we'll know we're really doing it when they start hating us.
We'll know we're really doing it when they don't just think we're weird, but they think we're dangerous.
When they think that we're
insane. When our existence threatens the people who love and create these often
demonic social orders, right? Cain killed Abel because Abel's existence as a
righteous person was a threat to him. The Jewish authorities had to crucify
Christ because his very existence was a threat to them.
And most of us today, so far, are so conformed to the social order that we're not threat
to anybody.
But we can be.
And together and working together, we can find salvation in the process.
Amen.
Well, that is our show for tonight, our Halloween episode.
So thank you everyone for listening.
If you can get through to us live,
we'd still love to hear from you.
You can email us at LordOfSpirits.ation.faith.com.
You can send us a message or a Facebook page
or you can leave us a voice mail at speakpipe.com slash LordOfSpirits.
And join us for our live broadcasts on the second
and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 PM Eastern,
4 PM Pacific, Tuesday morning, next week, out in the suburbs.
And if you are on Facebook, you can like our page.
join our discussion group.
Also, everyone, make sure you check out the new Ancient Feat. Radio app on both Android
and iPhone, if you have one of those machines.
Leave reviews and ratings everywhere, but most importantly, please share the show with
a friend whom you know is going to love it.
And finally, be sure to go to www.anxiafate.com, stroke support, and help make sure we and lots
of AFR podcasts are stay on the air.
And don't worry this weekend.
No one likes your kids enough to give them free drugs.
Thank you, good night.
And may God bless, keep you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of
Ancient Faith Radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
than thousands of thousands.
saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.